Guide to the Counseling Center Records, 1950-1970 UA.09.11.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Counseling Center records
1950-1970
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Counseling Center
UA.09.11.0001
3.2 Linear Feet
The Counseling Center offered general psychological counseling to students, faculty, staff, and the Durham community, particularly in the areas of career planning and education, and personal and social development. It also provided students with information about jobs, graduate school, financial aid, foreign study, and employment. Records contain printed material relating to the Counseling Center and its predecessor, the Bureau of Testing and Guidance, including correspondence, reports, memoranda, financial statements, printed matters, and other materials. The materials range in date from 1950-1970.
Historical note
Since the 1920s, various counseling services had been offered by the University in cooperation with organizations such as the "Y" and the Southern Women's Educational Alliance. The Bureau of Testing and Guidance was created in 1944 to provide educational and vocational testing services to the University and on occasion to the Durham community. The first staff members were James M. Slay, an Assistant Dean of Trinity College, assistant director Jay Ostwalt, and administrative assistant Mrs. R.E. Lee. The office offered pre-college testing of applicants, placement testing, career counseling, and aptitude testing. It underwent major reorganization in the fall of 1950.
In the 1950s, Henry Weitz became director of the Bureau, the staff was enlarged, and the program's focus was changed to emphasize counseling, with testing placed in a supporting role. In 1964, the name of the organization was changed from the Bureau of Testing and Guidance to the University Counseling Center, further accentuating the role that counseling had come to play in operations.
As its primary mission, the Counseling Center offered general psychological counseling to students, faculty, staff, and the Durham community, particularly in the areas of career planning and education, as well as personal and social development. It also provided students with information concerning jobs, graduate school, financial aid, foreign study, and employment. In 1977, the Counseling Center merged with Student Mental Health Services to form Counseling and Psychological Services, or CAPS.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains materials pertaining to the Counseling Center and its predecessor, the Bureau of Testing and Guidance, including printed informational materials, correspondence, reports, memoranda, financial statements, test booklets, draft proposals for an M.A. in guidance at Duke, and other materials. Included are annual reports, 1950-1969; summaries of placement test scores by school and major field, 1951-1956; annual budgets, 1951/52 to 1969/70; staff research reports, 1952 to 1966 concerning placement test performance and predictive value; and brochures and clippings describing the Center and its services. The correspondence and memoranda concern planning for a proposed graduate program in counselor training (1950 to 1953) and guidance training institute (1958), placement tests (1962), the organizational name change (1964), and practices at other institutions (1959-1960). Final annual budgets (oversize) are also included, covering the years 1954 to 1970, as well as a ten year placement testing study covering the years 1951-1960 (oversize).
Provenance
The Counseling Center records were received by the Duke University Archives as a transfer from the Counseling Center in September 1976 and August 1977 (accession numbers UA76--153, UA77--109).
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Counseling in higher education -- United States; Psychological Tests -- Analysis; Vocational guidance -- North Carolina -- Durham; Ballantyne, Robert H.; Duke University. Counseling Center; Weitz, Henry; Duke University. Bureau of Testing and Guidance
- Counseling Center records, 1950-1970
  - Informational Materials, Publications Concerning Center, Memoranda, 1952-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Test Bulletins, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Placement Testing Program Interpretive Manuals, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Occupational and Professional School Placement of the Graduating Class of 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Foreign Language and Math Placement Testing, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Service Bulletins, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Staff Research Reports and Memoranda, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Staff Research Reports and Memoranda, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Staff Research Reports and Memoranda, 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Placement Test Examiner's Manual (Reading), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Binder: Annual Budgets, 1951/52-1969/70; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Binder: Placement Test Performance by Major Field; Frequencies, Means, and Standard Deviations; Unit Frequencies, 1951-1952; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Binder: Placement Test Performance by Major Field Groups, 1951-1953; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Draft Proposal for Guidance Training Institute at Duke, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Placement Testing Revision, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mathematics Placement Test Cumulative Scores and Analysis, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Counseling Center Name Change, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Memoranda, Correspondence, Annual Report (1958-59), Case Load Survey, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - M.A. in Guidance, Announcement, Correspondence, Memoranda, Proposals, Requirements, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Binder: Research Reports, 1952-1965; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Binder: Annual Reports, 1950/51-1959/60; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Binder: Annual Survey of Placement Test Scores by School, 1951-1953 (Box 1)
  - Binder: Annual Survey of Placement Test Scores by School, 1951-1953 (Box 1)
  - Binder: Annual Reports, 1960/61-1968/69; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Sample Personality, Vocational, and Educational Assesment Tests, 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Placement Testing Study - 10 Year, 1951-1960 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Bureau of Testing and Guidance Budget, 1954/55-1969/70 (Oversize-folder 2)